Govinda Das ji: And stop.
Sattvastha Ventures: I think we can start with session 4 together.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Namaste, everyone, and I welcome you all to Day 4.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And…
Dr. Karan Mittal: We need to begin with that exercise, but before that, we'll just quickly go through what we did yesterday.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And yesterday, we basically saw two frameworks.
Dr. Karan Mittal: One was the undercurrent framework, and then the bias framework.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sue?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, kind of, you know, kind of anchoring from there, we also saw how sanskaras kind of affect our perceptions about things, and how the Indian knowledge
Dr. Karan Mittal: system views Sanskaras as probably the substratum over which our decisions are based, and how… why working on sanscaras are equally… is equally important. So… so today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: To begin with, let's probably work on that transpersonal exercise. This exercise is probably a combination of theories of transpersonal regression work and transactional analysis. These are two, modern-day psychotherapeutic techniques, and we have been… this exercise basically taken in, techniques from that exercise and integrated with our SANSCAR framework to work on
Dr. Karan Mittal: That particular sensor easily.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I request you all to kind of, you know, close your eyes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, probably, bring in to your awareness that particular sanskara.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That you have kind of selected to work upon.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… just be aware of that particular Sanskara belief.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I didn't… trade… That you might have contemplated upon.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… As we do that, Just be aware of how it has affected your life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably both, good and bad.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How it has affected your life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The decisions you took.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And those decisions, how it changed the course of your life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: or on a day-to-day basis, how it affects you. Like I said yesterday, speaking quickly, or speaking without waiting for my turn, how it kind of pushes my clients a bit back.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how it affects you on a day-to-day basis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also be aware of the emotion that Sanskara brings for you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: For me, it could be, like, frustration, because I try to work on it, it still is a trait in me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's also frustration, because sometimes it… it triggers my client wrongly, and then I feel frustrated that I could not wait for my turn.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so, which emotion? Frustration, anger, sadness?
Dr. Karan Mittal: In addition, jealousy… Any of the emotions that this vast promise car generates for you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now I want you to visualize that particular Age when you got it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You got that belief or that sanskara from the person
Dr. Karan Mittal: I want you to visualize that younger self in front of you. So, for me, it would be that 10-year-old in front of me. 10-year-old Karan. So, it could be any age that you have kind of heard that Sanskara for the first time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Let's visualize that particular age of yours, that child version of yours, standing in front of you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And as you do that, Just express to that child in his language, whichever language you spoke.
Dr. Karan Mittal: As a child, your mother tongue?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just tell that child how this belief is dysfunctional for you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How it is affecting you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How it is affecting the adult of today, and how it has affected him until today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe just 3, 4, 5 sentences, but not mechanical ones. Your real experience with that particular sanskara.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, be aware of the emotion that's coming up for you as an adult. As you speak, that experience of yours, that suffering of yours to that child.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And just make him aware that this particular
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thing that he got from that adult, that, that relative, or parent, or teacher.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's dysfunctioning for him as well as you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's not serving any purpose.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now I want you to visualize
Dr. Karan Mittal: That adult from whom you bought that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Particular belief in front of both of you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Keep both your shoulders… keep both your palms on the shoulders of that child, maybe 10-year-old, 8-year-old. If he's a teenager, you can keep
Dr. Karan Mittal: One of your palms on his shoulder, as if you are supporting him.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And inspire, encourage the child.
Dr. Karan Mittal: To tell that particular a trade figure.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That particular parent, teacher, or relative.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That this does not belong to me. It belongs to you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I choose to give it back to you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I choose to give that particular vasana, that particular… frame it in words, I choose to give that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Need of being a fast speaker, or replying quickly back to you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This is not serving any purpose to me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I don't need it anymore.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I give it back to you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now, the fourth question, which I didn't share purposefully on the group.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the due course of experiencing this Anskarvasana pattern belief system.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what part of you did you lose? Like, for me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because I have this habit of speaking fast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or, or, or replying quickly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'm not waiting for my turn. I lost my patience.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I lost my peace of mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, I lost my peace of mind, because every time my mind is just racing to compete.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the, to give the answer as quickly as possible.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So just be aware of that particular trait of yours that you lost, kind of, you lose.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or you kind of give… had to give up.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the process of… performing this pattern, really, for Vasna.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now retrieve that particular trait, that quality, that positive…
Dr. Karan Mittal: trait back from the adult, from that particular parent-teacher.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or a relative. That I take back my peace of mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I take back my patience.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I take back that patient that was originally mine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we are doing an exchange. We are giving him
Dr. Karan Mittal: what wasn't ours, and he kind of had imposed upon us. We are giving him back that belief, and we're taking that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Original part of ours, that is patience, peace of mind, happiness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whatever it is, we're retrieving it back from it, because we need to complete that exchange.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I know I did it very quickly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But this could be done a few more times in your own, maybe.
Dr. Karan Mittal: visualization after the session for a day or two, to work on that sense card more deeply. You'll get more insights on
Dr. Karan Mittal: How it affected you, and what all did you lose in turn?
Dr. Karan Mittal: By, by absorbing that substance.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So once we're there, we have taken back what was originally yours.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You can open your eyes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I just want one… one person or two persons to share how it was… how was it for you. Could you… could you get in touch with
Dr. Karan Mittal: What did you lose, and… What did you kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, how did it affect your lives? Which person was it?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, grumsy, or… I cannot see videos, so I don't know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Could you just share a bit in a word, like, in a few… one or two sentences?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Vikram Chakilam: Am I young?
Vikram Chakilam: Samskara was, angry, anger, anger.
Vikram Chakilam: And,
Vikram Chakilam: One thing I'm in Dalama is, like, did I get it from my father, who is also very angry? Or it's my nature.
Vikram Chakilam: Absolutely. I know we talked about astronomy.
Vikram Chakilam: So, that I was not sure, but definitely I've seen my father anger so many times.
Vikram Chakilam: I don't take it as a negative, because he's… Very good in all aspects.
Vikram Chakilam: Never talks bad about an event, till now.
Vikram Chakilam: So, his nature is maybe angry, but it's only for a short time.
Vikram Chakilam: He… he doesn't have any grudges.
Vikram Chakilam: So, maybe I did not get it from him.
Vikram Chakilam: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Vikram Chakilam: But,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Some things?
Vikram Chakilam: And.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yep.
Vikram Chakilam: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, sometimes… see, astrology could be an explanation for that whole dynamics. So, like, we have different explanations for the same thing. So, still, you could work on that Sanskara. Maybe from the 100% of your anger, maybe 10% or 20% comes from your father.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, working even on that 10-20% will give you some… some insights and some… some improvement in that 10 minutes your first, though maybe the rest, 70-80, is from… from your own, maybe, astrological chart, etc.
Vikram Chakilam: Beautiful.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so this was what we saw yesterday, and then the current, how structurally each of the four, domains, work, and how the current also kind of conditions our biases, etc. So that… that's what we discussed yesterday. Let's kind of move…
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this is something for you to take away that, you know?
Dr. Karan Mittal: As a therapist, we usually are in the mode of finding what's wrong in the client, or what exactly
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, that's the difference between the, the earlier Western psychology. Right now, of course, the Western psychology is also kind of revamping itself. The third generation therapies, et cetera, are now, working on mindfulness and all that stuff. But… but it also, the earlier version saw what was just wrong in the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But a non-judging therapist knows that, you know, that it's like the river analogy, the non-judging therapist watches the river, knowing that the debris, whatever is wrong, will pass. But the judging therapist is always looking at the debris. So… so when you're just looking at the voids.
Dr. Karan Mittal: then you are already in a messiah mode or in a helper mode to kind of work or rectify the faults. So that becomes important that you also understand that you… you are just playing a small part in working in this whole revert flow of the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you are working with the debris, but at the same time, you know that the inner core of the client is as clean or as fresh as that river water flowing. So that's… that's the disposition that we, need to develop.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Rabbiji?
Govinda Das ji: Yes, coming over to here.
Govinda Das ji: Are you able to do that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, yes, we are able to do it.
Govinda Das ji: There are some video problems that is coming.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure.
Govinda Das ji: Yes.
Govinda Das ji: You're able to hear me?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Luji cleared it.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah.
Govinda Das ji: So, we can start.
Govinda Das ji: Karin, you can start?
Govinda Das ji: We do? Yeah, I'm sorry.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, yes, yes, sorry, yeah. So, I think now we are… we are, we are seeing different, different frameworks, and today also, at the end, we'll also kind of take an example how to integrate these frameworks, and the… the next framework that we are also going to see is the Trigona framework.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, now, as I, as, like, as a disposition, I would like to clarify that, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This is a way of analyzing
Dr. Karan Mittal: the client, but it's not… like, you cannot impose your moral bias of a scripture, etc, onto the client. It gives you an analysis of which mode the client is in, and where do you need to take that client to kind of help the client better.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But you cannot make it like a moral bias that you're a client to Tamsik hair, Tamsik Suchega, or whatever, this client is Tamsik, and, you know, things will not affect him, this will not help him, etc. So we need to not see it as a moral bias or a moral compartment, but we just need to see it as a disposition. And also, the modes of the client keeps on changing, whichever modes we'll be discussing, whether it's
Dr. Karan Mittal: Laguna, or a bunch of Oshas, which will be seen on day 5. They keep on changing, so you don't put a stamp or a label on the client that, okay, this client is thumbsick, and he will respond thumbsickly in all aspects of his life. That's not the case.
Dr. Karan Mittal: With regards to the issue that we are dealing with, we kind of try to analyze that what mode the client is coming in from.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, as you all know, that… that there are these three modes. You have heard, heard, read in scriptures, heard, etc. So, saqvar, Rajas, and Tamas, and all three are different dispositions that, that a client can be in.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Mostly, as a therapist, our need is to kind of facilitate a mode where you are in the sarvik state, and also you bring the client in the sarvik state. That's where the actual healing or therapy happens.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you yourself are in a Rajasic state of wanting to help the client, wanting to help the client, wanting to help the client, and just thinking of solutions, thinking of, you know, different, different means, giving advices, etc, then you, in your Rajasik state, and client probably in Rajasik or Tamsik State, healing and therapy world.
Dr. Karan Mittal: or you are in tamsic state, you want to… you are kind of taking in 4, 5, 6, 7 clients every day, or doing it, you know, out of boredom, or out of compulsion, healing will not help.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So the goal of the session is you being in the Southwik State, and also trying to
Dr. Karan Mittal: Bring that client into the psychic state, and then the healing is automatic.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then, of course, you need to add a few tools as flavors and as help… as helping tools for the client, but once the client gets into that self-contemplative mode, then automatically they give it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Rubju, would you like to expand on that?
Govinda Das ji: I don't see… you already put PPT?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is BPD visible to everyone?
Rutuja Nayak: Yes.
Vikram Chakilam: Yes.
Govinda Das ji: Alright.
Govinda Das ji: I'm not about…
Dr. Karan Mittal: I will stop and reshare, probably that will end up a lot.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is it visible now, Roger?
Govinda Das ji: Yes, now it can.
Govinda Das ji: Correct, yeah.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, thank you for, holding on, so…
Govinda Das ji: The… when you see purely from the spiritual perspective.
Govinda Das ji: there is a tendency to undermine Rajas and Thomas.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, certainly we need to do that.
Govinda Das ji: But again, when we operate in this world, Right?
Govinda Das ji: In the word of sattva, is goodness, Sartu also means substance.
Govinda Das ji: Sattu also means essence. Sattu also denotes clarity.
Govinda Das ji: Imagine if you have only Satva Guna.
Govinda Das ji: And the world is functioning in Rajo Buddha.
Govinda Das ji: Then you cannot contribute much.
Govinda Das ji: Because creation happens in Rajo Buddha.
Govinda Das ji: And Vishran, Nidra, happens in Tamogoda.
Govinda Das ji: There may be greater disadvantage of Tamoguna, but there are some advantages of Tamoguna.
Govinda Das ji: there could be some disadvantage of the Rajo Guna. There are many advantages of the Rajo Guna.
Govinda Das ji: One of the drawbacks of Satvagoda is it makes you contented.
Govinda Das ji: fulfilled.
Govinda Das ji: Satisfied.
Govinda Das ji: It takes away your ambition.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, Chanakya… He says… A king who is satisfied.
Govinda Das ji: And an entrepreneur who's satisfied is an enemy of the king. Enemy of the kingdom.
Govinda Das ji: Because a nation has to always operate in Rajoguna with the foundation of Sakhoguna.
Govinda Das ji: The family has to operate in Rajo Guna while people maintaining their Sakhoguna.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, from the purely psychological and the creation perspective, all the three gunas are integrated with the greater amount of sakura.
Govinda Das ji: But when we hear the spiritual discourse.
Govinda Das ji: It is but natural, it is not wrong, it is correct. Rajas and Tamas are undermined.
Govinda Das ji: We were discussing yesterday.
Govinda Das ji: like, for a teacher, a Brahmana, if a Brahmana is not simply a jati, it is a disposition
Govinda Das ji: Satisfaction is very important for a Brahmana.
Govinda Das ji: Ambition is very good for a kshatriya.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, what is sattva? It is luminosity, you know, there is clarity.
Govinda Das ji: It is balance, yoga.
Govinda Das ji: But unfortunately, if you are starting your life, balance does not work.
Govinda Das ji: If you're studying in the school or college, you can't teach children to be balanced. During examination, they will have disruption of that balance. They'll focus more on studying and appearing for their examination.
Govinda Das ji: If you studied the business, You cannot afford to be balanced.
Govinda Das ji: Overall, life could be balanced, but on a day-to-day basis, if you're rigid about balancing, you could balance, but you may not grow.
Govinda Das ji: So that is the quality of sattoguna, equanimity, the quality that allows accurate perception and steady response.
Govinda Das ji: They're not.
Govinda Das ji: That is the beauty of sattva. Sattva gives the perspective.
Govinda Das ji: Rajo gives action.
Govinda Das ji: And Tamor gives rest.
Govinda Das ji: Right? If you have the Tamil perspective, then everything is topsy-turvy.
Govinda Das ji: If you have Rajo perspective, everywhere you see competition.
Govinda Das ji: If your sattvo perspective, your vision is clear, and based upon that clear vision, your Rajo and Tamo are integrated, they become a support system, rather than becoming a conflicting system.
Govinda Das ji: Alright?
Govinda Das ji: So, what is supplements? Clarity.
Govinda Das ji: Rajas… Ranjati Iti Raja. Raja, the world of Praja, also come from Rajo Gun only.
Govinda Das ji: Prajati Iti Praja. Ranjati Iti Raja.
Govinda Das ji: If the Raja is not entertaining the Praja properly, you cannot tell… the king cannot tell a citizen, you know, hunger is a state of consciousness.
Govinda Das ji: That is not his job. That is the job of a sage.
Govinda Das ji: Sage can say that, oh, hunger is a state of mind.
Govinda Das ji: The king has to work hard to provide the resources.
Govinda Das ji: A father cannot tell his children, you know what?
Govinda Das ji: One should be satisfied with whatever we have. Half a roti, one-fourth of the roti. That philosophical understanding of sattvaguna becomes violent towards the children.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, what is Raja? Raja means movement.
Govinda Das ji: desire You know, agitation.
Govinda Das ji: It is impossible, if you are functioning, doing something tangible, to produce something, you're not restless, you're not educated.
Govinda Das ji: Because that is the mode will bring that kind of quality.
Govinda Das ji: The quality of wanting, striving, reaching.
Govinda Das ji: What is it?
Govinda Das ji: driven.
Govinda Das ji: If there is a clarity, and there is a… there is an… there is an aspect of drive, so Rajo and sattva becomes Raja, and
Govinda Das ji: mantra, the Maha Mantri, in the astrological chart.
Govinda Das ji: There is an amazing concept of when sun god, sun planet, is influenced by guru, that is Brahaspati, Jupiter.
Govinda Das ji: They come together, and there is a sattva, and there is also action.
Govinda Das ji: They work together. If the Mars is connected to Jupiter, they work together properly. There is an action, and there is also
Govinda Das ji: Proper identity, proper disposition.
Govinda Das ji: Thomas, inertia. Imagine.
Govinda Das ji: There is no tamau, and you don't feel exhausted only.
Govinda Das ji: In the… in the army, when you're working in Siachen Glacier.
Govinda Das ji: There is a rule for the soldiers, they do not put their hand on an open fire.
Govinda Das ji: Because it is so cold, you don't even get to know that your skin is burning.
Govinda Das ji: Touching your bones.
Govinda Das ji: Going to the flesh.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Because there is soooo much of…
Govinda Das ji: You know, cold, you're not aware also.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, heaviness is required, because heaviness comes when you are exhausted.
Govinda Das ji: dullness.
Govinda Das ji: Obscured, you're obscured, the clarity is not there.
Govinda Das ji: the qualitative withdrawal. This is not sattva withdrawal.
Govinda Das ji: This is a tamel withdravel, caused by pain, anger, frustration.
Govinda Das ji: One is stuck.
Govinda Das ji: collapse.
Govinda Das ji: You know, what is it? Obscured. One is clear, one is driven, one is obscured.
Govinda Das ji: Tamoguna is like adding hing.
Govinda Das ji: You don't add half a kilo in.
Govinda Das ji: You are cooking rice, rice is like sattva, fire is like rajo, and adding some flavor, whether it is salt or ham, is very minuscule. So therefore, when they're integrated in this way.
Govinda Das ji: Rajo, Satwa, and Tama, that defines your personality, that defines your profession, that defines your mindset also.
Govinda Das ji: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: how will… how will the clients in having a particular dominant gonna actually present themselves? So I've given… I've given the… the criteria, like, a few, few thoughts. Like, a Tamsai client usually is kind of hopeless about the whole situation, is depressive.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, there's a sense of helplessness, there's a sense of negative acceptance to the whole situation. So that's how, you know, a thumbsick client will kind of, like, oh, we cannot do anything about it, so I've accepted… So, if he has accepted the situation, then why is he sitting with you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So there is… there is an element of Tamsic disposition or perspective to the whole thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And a Rajase client will want to do more than what is needed, okay? So he will try to kind of do everything that is possible, will put in more efforts than what it is needed, then will have a high verbal output, like, will speak fast, we'll
Dr. Karan Mittal: say a lot of things, and will present too many problems at one go. So, that's the Rajasik client for you. So, most of the time, you'll see that
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Rajasik line is not aware about… of his emotions, of what actually the problem is. He might give you many things, but he doesn't himself know, because the mind is also racing, so there's no grounding in that particular client. So he will speak, he will share memories, he will share,
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably situations at home. He'll be speaking quickly, but he won't be aware of what actually is happening within
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So, like, yesterday also we saw… we saw that someone was describing something, but then we started digging, digging, digging, the actual problem was something else. Okay, so a client who is in that mode will keep on… keep on
Dr. Karan Mittal: sharing the problem, but he won't be aware of the actual issues or emotions. Whereas at the Tamsik client, Tamsik client knows the issue, but he has kind of distanced himself negatively. Internally, he wants to resolve the issue, but that's a sense of negative conditioning that has happened in the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And a Southwik client… see, so it's not that a Southwik client cannot have problems, okay? So… but a Southwik client is… otherwise, Southwik client is sitting with you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: He knows there's a problem, he knows why he's sitting with you, because he needs solutions to the problem, he needs tools to address that problem. So, he has that disposition where he's composed, he knows the problem.
Dr. Karan Mittal: He's willing to accept his mistakes, because Sakwa is also Guyana. So, also, the Ghana of your own shortcomings is what a Saka client is readily accepting.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so, he's okay with you becoming harsh, it's okay with you kind of pushing him, everything, because he's in a state of wanting solutions. So, sattva is not that he doesn't… he or she doesn't have problems. Sattva is basically, wanting solutions, and that's why he's kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: sitting with you. So, so, so, in relationship issues, you'll see this very, very, very commonly. Like, yesterday we saw that example where I said he was not ready to accept that there, there was the… that he was saying that there has been no divorce in his family. Proper Rajasik light.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, proper Raja Singhang, wanting to do too many things, too many things, too many things, but at the core, not wanting to accept, okay, there has been a divorce in my family, this relationship is not working, etc. I need to find a solution to this problem. But how? In a hyperm. Not accepting a part of reality, not getting in touch with emotions, but just being
Dr. Karan Mittal: Descriptive of the problem and trying to fix it superficially.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's how Thomas, Rajasth, and Satwa kind of show up in sessions. And a client is usually… one of the gunas is dominant with regards to one particular problem.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, as I said in the beginning, you know, if the client is… if you are Rajasik and the client is Rajasik, you are just saying solutions, you are just trying to help, you have that helper syndrome in you, the messiah syndrome in you, and the client is just accepting, accepting for the sake of accepting, and nothing will come up. It will just be spiral.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you're in the thumbsick mode, if you're tired, you are wanting to… sometimes… oh, it also happens that, you know,
Dr. Karan Mittal: in spiritual counseling, etc, you don't like a particular person, but that particular person has come to you for advice, through reference or something, or you have developed a negative attitude towards that person because of your sales and you hearing from different people. So at that time, you are already in that tamsic mode of, you know, not liking that person. The client is also probably in the thumbsic mode, so that session will be dead. That therapy is not going to go anywhere.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So it's… it's imperative that at least you are in that subject mode during the session, and then you kind of do all the things to bring that client into subject mode.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, and also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: As Privy was also yesterday saying, that, you know, in Ayurveda, we apply that oil in the head, take that machinery, and all. So, bringing into these three gunas, changing the guna of the client is not just by talking.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Over a period of time, when you develop that rapport with the client, can you also advise a few other things that can bring a client into the buna that you are wanting the client to be in?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so… so, I think at the… at the bottom of the slide, there are these three things where you kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: are trying to analyze what is your disposition in a session, and that would be a good takeaway exercise for you also, that whatever counseling you have done, or how you have behaved with your kids, or your students, because many of you are
Dr. Karan Mittal: are also educators. Which dominant mode you are in while you are doing whatever you're doing as a parent, teacher, or a counselor?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Are you… are you more, like, when you're interacting with the kids or your counselors, are you more into the sluggish, tired, more…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Are you… are you, are you hyper and trying to resolve things and, helping people, trying to help more than what is necessary? Or you are trying… at the majority of the times, you are in that sathwick mode. So you will see the difference in that opposite person also, based on your disposition. The disposition in the person opposite to you will also change.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is crucial.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore… Sattva is not necessarily saintly.
Govinda Das ji: Suppose another kind of bondage, a bondage of fulfillment, contentment.
Govinda Das ji: not being more than required. It's enough, why should I worry?
Govinda Das ji: Right? So therefore, sattva is also a mundane quality one.
Govinda Das ji: It is not a spiritual quality, it has an impetus for spirituality.
Govinda Das ji: Satoa?
Govinda Das ji: Can be used for progressive life, because that is the foundation that does not make us restless.
Govinda Das ji: In fact, in the Bhagavatam Kapila Muni, one who taught the Sankhya philosophy.
Govinda Das ji: He told his mother, even devotion, right?
Govinda Das ji: When there are debates in this world, whether religion is good or bad.
Govinda Das ji: Now, this was preconceived by the sages thousands of years ago.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, even bhakti was categorized into 3 levels.
Govinda Das ji: There is Tamogun Bhakti, there is Rajo Gun Bhakti, and there is Satvogan Bhakti.
Govinda Das ji: What is Tamogunu Bhakti? Very dangerous.
Govinda Das ji: You know, the Tamogurta Bhakti creates a superiority complex.
Govinda Das ji: Does not see anybody other than one's own self.
Govinda Das ji: One's own practice, One's own's parameters. And it is violent and separatist.
Govinda Das ji: The Mogulu Bhakti wants to kill everybody else.
Govinda Das ji: Rajo go to Bhakti is competitive.
Govinda Das ji: If I have 2 feet DTs.
Govinda Das ji: Then your competitor wants to bring 2.5 feet details.
Govinda Das ji: the Vigraha.
Govinda Das ji: There is Rajo Guna, and only in Satva Guna, there is a cooperation. Sattvoguna gives rise to cooperation, Rajo Ghuna gives rise to competition, Tamoguna gives rise to conflict.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, it is important that…
Govinda Das ji: The… this therapist, therefore, some time.
Govinda Das ji: When we are dealing with conflict, we actually make people the product.
Govinda Das ji: When you do Prada N, What does it do? It actually minimizes your blood pressure.
Govinda Das ji: with few Omkar and Pranayan.
Govinda Das ji: Even though one may be prominently in Rajoguna, Tamoguna, If they become pacified.
Govinda Das ji: then it is very easy to speak. And you can see that when people are angry, upset, hurtful, their breathing increases.
Govinda Das ji: But when you pranaim, Immediately, there is a major tone, slow not softwise.
Govinda Das ji: Temperature has not risen.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, it is important to understand sattva is not saintly, it also has its limitation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, how do you… how do we understand whether
Dr. Karan Mittal: when we are sitting in that session or that counseling work, are we in that sattu mode? If you are really in the satu mode, you don't need to perform.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it will automatically come to you, like, and that happens with self-work and being aware of your thoughts, your body language, emotions. Over a period of time, it happens. But as we saw in one of the sessions, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's not about performance. You cannot perform to be successful, because you might perform with body language, but internally your thoughts and your emotions are still racing. Your expressions might change. And clients, when they are there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: looking at you, and there's a very close eye contact, which you can probably… that's why I suggested
Dr. Karan Mittal: Keeping your videos on. When there's a very close eye contact, your eyes and your expressions speak a lot. So, clients catch those cues, and they understand how much present you are into that session. So, if you are feeling bored by a client, or you're feeling agitated by a client, somewhere or the other, that body language is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so it's all about not performing, it's all about imbibing that supaguna, and it also is like a hat. So, it's also like a hat, that when you're sitting into that room, it's also that
Dr. Karan Mittal: that if you are probably at 10 in your suburbana, that plus 2 plus 3 happens with practice, because you're sitting on a chair as a therapist. So, so, it's not about performance, it's about changing your disposition.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, Sue?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe, maybe at the end, maybe one of the exercises, I'll demonstrate this, that how you can probably, you know, change the disposition of client by changing your disposition, and also by the right questioning, and that we'll be doing as a demo, where we'll try to bring that client into a circle mode.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, when you are that, you know, when, when you are that Rajasic.
Dr. Karan Mittal: therapist, you are automatically there to just give solutions, and without hearing the full thing, like, like I was doing yesterday. Without hearing the client fully, I was just asking more and more and more questions. And so that was, like, me, Rajasik, and the client, also Rajasik.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But… but if you are… if you are into that subtle mode, then of course the gearing will improve, and the client will… and also the questioning, because you are that empty container in subtle mode, the questioning style will also change. That will also try to bring the client into that subtle mode.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so what we do, and that's… that's what CBT and all the modern-day therapies also do, is we ask the right questions to make this client self-contemplative about the whole situation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, and also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: there are techniques in NLP and other therapy where me kind of, you know, controlling my breath will also help the client control the breath unconsciously.
Dr. Karan Mittal: me changing my body language, or me changing the way I look at the client, etc, or the way I'm sitting, the way my body is moving, will also create an equal ripple effect in the client, and the client's, you know, body language, breadth rate, etc. will start changing. Of course, it takes time, but sometimes when you're dealing with a hyper client, etc, this helps, because you cannot tell the client to speak softly, go slowly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because they are in that… Catharsis mode, or in that venting out mode.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this… these all things help, it's… it's like the ripple effect. Your subtle mode will start, you know, changing the mode in the opposite.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's true, Jay.
Govinda Das ji: Yes.
Govinda Das ji: So again, just like we were discussing about the chittal and samskaras.
Govinda Das ji: you know, the… the whole concept of Guna
Govinda Das ji: in the Bhagavad Gita 14 chapter.
Govinda Das ji: When you read Three Gunas, it talks about the battle.
Govinda Das ji: In the 7th Kento, the Bhagavatam also speaks about that. In the Mahavara, it is elaborately explained.
Govinda Das ji: So, based upon the elaborate explanation of Mahabharat, in our app, also, we want the parameters.
Govinda Das ji: Are you not?
Govinda Das ji: Today, what is my position? Where do I stand? Whether I'm in Tamahuna, Rajobuna, Satobuna, you can see that.
Govinda Das ji: You know, very, very deeply, Mahabharat explains about three modes of material nature. Bhagavad Gita focuses on the substance, because Krishna had only 40 minutes to speak.
Govinda Das ji: So, what does the three modes of material nature do? Actually, the three modes, three gunas.
Govinda Das ji: They keep us in this platform.
Govinda Das ji: As long as these three modes are there, it creates a… it creates a vicious circle.
Govinda Das ji: And that vicious circle, what does it do? It gives rise to response. We react.
Govinda Das ji: If there is more Raja and more Tamil, there is more response. If there is more response, there are more nuisome scars.
Govinda Das ji: Right? If there are new samskaras, that becomes part of the god, the stock, the chitta. Chitta is more and more covered.
Govinda Das ji: Right? The ISCON founder, Srila Prabhupad would mention
Govinda Das ji: As the gunas become deeper and deeper.
Govinda Das ji: Your covering becomes increased more and more.
Govinda Das ji: And that is what called is animalistic life.
Govinda Das ji: That is called as animal life, and therefore, the Puranas talk about 84 lakh species of life.
Govinda Das ji: It may sound fantastic.
Govinda Das ji: But this 84 lakh species of life is nothing but different variations of three modes of material nature.
Govinda Das ji: We will have the body, we will have the conditioning, we will have the consequences of that reaction, as much as we accumulate the gunas.
Govinda Das ji: And depending upon what speed we accumulate.
Govinda Das ji: And once the three gunas disappear, there is no more material on them.
Govinda Das ji: Huh?
Govinda Das ji: Because body certainly is made of earth, water, fire, air, ether.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Even those earth, even water, Even fire!
Govinda Das ji: the… the Sankhya speaks about… Maybe there are 50 varieties of fire.
Govinda Das ji: Right? There are so many varieties of fire. Generally, we say red. Everybody's blood is red.
Govinda Das ji: That is correct, but if you talk to the doctor or pathologist, they will actually create such a deeper layers of varieties of blood.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, there is a truth in saying that everybody's blood is the same, it is all right, but also there is a truth, there is a variation, there is a variety. So, therefore, this constant virtuous and vicious circle is operating all the time, and therefore, this material world
Govinda Das ji: Or our entrepreneurship world, our institution, our organization, our home, is always functioning based upon these three modes of material nature.
Govinda Das ji: If there is a Rajo match, then there is a battle. Tamil much?
Govinda Das ji: There is so much of lethargy. Imagine husband and wife and children, everybody's in Tamogana, their house will be totally unclean.
Govinda Das ji: Because they're completely comfortable in being that kind of horse.
Govinda Das ji: And imagine you have a very strong satuaguna person.
Govinda Das ji: Always cleaning everything.
Govinda Das ji: and she or he has a personality who is Tamogodha, it doesn't matter their intent.
Govinda Das ji: It doesn't matter if they're a jaati.
Govinda Das ji: It doesn't matter their faith, they may have a same faith, that conflict between Tamil and Satwa, what does it do? It creates a conflict. So this is very important to understand.
Govinda Das ji: That gunas create response, response create new samskaras, new samskaras create stock of samskara, and then that impacts the variation of your guna.
Govinda Das ji: You know, your satma reduces, your Raja increases your tamaw increases.
Govinda Das ji: So therefore, through food, through yoga, through spirituality, through dharmic activities, one can create proper balance according to her disposition, and use that guna for our growth and progress.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'll just add a bit here. So… so what differs, what… what is different, or what separates the IKS framework is, like, I also… I also trained in many Western psychological methods.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So what happens is, we usually target one particular thing, okay? Maybe the behavior, the emotion, the sanskaras in, like, by regression therapy, etc. But the IKS framework targets this whole you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And it also targets, like, it will target the Sanskara-guna response separately. It will also target the pathway between sanskara and the response, the response and the guna, and the guna and the formation of new sanskara. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we see a person as a whole, and rather than focusing on just one aspect and expecting this whole loop to collapse, we target every particular thing in a different, different, different way, and then we expect this whole loop to collapse in the IKS framework.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we've… we… the response that happens in our day-to-day, where we suggest changes, how to behave, etc. Guna happens on a physical level, Ayurveda level, on a timetable level, where we try to bring the client into more sacrabuna. Sanskara is something where we take the client back and try to
Dr. Karan Mittal: push or kind of find where did this belief or this pattern originate. So, every particular aspect, even here, and you'll also see in the Panchk Kosha, every particular aspect is targeted independently.
Dr. Karan Mittal: keeping the whole client, or the wholesome view in perspective. That is what is the difference in our Rishi Parampara and the Western methods, where there's a one segregated approach to the whole human being, and here, segregation exists, but with keeping the wholesome view in perspective. And that's how we also deal with
Dr. Karan Mittal: Kids, or with students, or with…
Dr. Karan Mittal: our clients, that we see what's the sanskara operating, we try to change guna in the session, after the session, giving some homework, and also response part is something that we deal in that 45 minutes to an hour to change the behavior of the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, that's it. So, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I'll probably, you know, we'll just do a small demo, and then maybe we can get into this exercise. I'll just give a 5-minute demo of how it works. So, this is the Guna Shift Drill, in my understanding. How by rightful questioning, how by kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: modulating your voice and expressions, etc. You can try bringing the client into the sattva mode of contemplation and realizing. That… that's what I'll try to demonstrate, and then you practice it within your trial for next 15 to 20 minutes. So, I would like… I would like someone to volunteer as a demo.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then… of course, it will be a tutorial, so I might have to explain in between, but if someone can volunteer, that would be great.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Anyone?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any… you don't need to work on something, like, in your life. You can also create a hypothetical case if you're uncomfortable sharing the details.
Anandini Sundari DD: Hi, Krishna?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Hare Krishna.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Boom, I'm just trying…
Anandini Sundari DD: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Anandini Sundari DD: Yes, I'm ready to…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, my just… yes.
Anandini Sundari DD: Yeah, I can be a client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Capital.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I'm shopping this screen so that you can see both of us. Yeah. Yes, Manhattan.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Would you like to bring up anything that… that you can share, and probably I can assist you a bit?
Anandini Sundari DD: Yeah. The way Prabhuji told, I'm always, in a mode of cleaning.
Anandini Sundari DD: I want the things very perfect. Neat and clean house.
Anandini Sundari DD: And always, helping out of the way I go and help people. Everybody tells me, why we're doing this?
Anandini Sundari DD: But I don't know the answer of that. That's the thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I think you mentioned two things. One is the cleaning thing, and one is the helping thing, right?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Why do… what do you feel? Why do you do either of the totals? Cleaning thing, as well as the healthy thing? What… what does it give you? What does it bring to your table?
Anandini Sundari DD: Actually, my father was like that, exam perfectionist.
Anandini Sundari DD: So, I think might be that, but…
Anandini Sundari DD: Now, I only feel better, I feel nice if the things are, room is clean and neat.
Anandini Sundari DD: And some mantra going on. I feel happy, I feel fresh, nice.
Anandini Sundari DD: That's the thing.
Anandini Sundari DD: So, I always like to be, you know, Keep things nicely.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And what about helping Bart?
Anandini Sundari DD: helping, I don't know. I like, you know, obsessive thing, I go and help people out of the way, even if that person has not behaved with me nicely. Still, I…
Anandini Sundari DD: And, it's when there is a need to help that person, I go and help.
Anandini Sundari DD: I mean, I forget only that person has not behaved properly with me, and I always behave nicely only.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How does it feel?
Anandini Sundari DD: Oh, no.
Anandini Sundari DD: I don't want… they are telling, yeah, okay, this person is nice. I don't want any fame, yeah, I don't want that they should, talk good about me.
Anandini Sundari DD: But I only feel good.
Anandini Sundari DD: Messive.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so you're okay with they probably not talking good about you, but you're still ready to help them?
Anandini Sundari DD: Yeah.
Anandini Sundari DD: Miss, I don't know from where this nature has come back, but from childhood, I'm like that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Anandini Sundari DD: Helping friends, giving notes.
Anandini Sundari DD: Everything.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And what's the worst thing that can happen if you don't help people? Like, suppose today you decide that I will not help anyone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How would.
Anandini Sundari DD: In life, it will not happen only like that.
Anandini Sundari DD: Not often only, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Hypothetically, what would happen?
Anandini Sundari DD: No, hypothetically, it is like that only, and if I'm not able to do that, I feel bad. I mean, sometimes I feel I'm like a people pleaser or what.
Anandini Sundari DD: Sorry I couldn't help, sorry I couldn't come. Like that, I talked with the person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… and… and why do you feel…
Dr. Karan Mittal: That you are a people pleaser?
Anandini Sundari DD: No, no!
Anandini Sundari DD: My son, my daughter, they tell me, you behave like a people blazer.
Anandini Sundari DD: You tell me, what's the need? If you're… even if I'm not okay physically, I'm ill, or sometimes I'm having backache, still you go and do… you just relax.
Anandini Sundari DD: Okay. Nothing will happen once you don't do the things.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Never.
Anandini Sundari DD: full life, you have done everything. Now, if you don't do nothing, nobody will say, Kirnahiki haze.
Anandini Sundari DD: But I don't know. So they asked me, why you do it?
Anandini Sundari DD: I said, I don't know, Ms. It's okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And just notice, Madhi, that, you know, while you're describing this whole thing, you're smiling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Though it's exhausting for you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Though… though you said… yeah, no, like, helping people out of the way, okay, even if… even when they say… they don't say nice about you, or they have done wrong to you. Just notice that. I'm not saying that it's wrong or right, I'm just saying just notice that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Anandini Sundari DD: is I don't get exhausted in helping if I'm not well, and still I'm doing it. I don't feel bad, I don't feel agitated, frustrated, nothing.
Anandini Sundari DD: I'm just happy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so my question is, what do you get? Like, what's internally changing?
Dr. Karan Mittal: When you help people out of the way.
Anandini Sundari DD: I am happy by seeing them happy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We're happy listening.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And is it possible that if you don't help them, you'll still feel happy?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, today, I, like, I asked your questions. Today, you decide that I won't help anyone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How would that feel?
Anandini Sundari DD: I don't know, I… First of all, I will not decide that. I cannot imagine.
Anandini Sundari DD: And…
Anandini Sundari DD: If the condition is like that, today I cannot help. That thing can happen. Suppose I'm having fever or some physical
Anandini Sundari DD: incapability of doing things.
Anandini Sundari DD: But still, something very grave happens.
Anandini Sundari DD: I will go and do it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. Again, Travel, I'll ask you the same question.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Suppose you decide today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That I will not help anyone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How will you feel?
Anandini Sundari DD: I'm not taught like that.
Anandini Sundari DD: I don't know what I'm liking.
Govinda Das ji: You can't even imagine.
Govinda Das ji: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, that's right. And I want you to, everyone, to observe that this is the time where she had to shift the lens from description to now, it was a contradictory question. It kind of changed the expression on her face, looking far, she was not able to visualize that version of herself. And there is where our interventions will happen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: She came to us… sorry, Madhji, I'll have to describe this a bit. I will, of course, not do full analysis, but.
Anandini Sundari DD: Yeah, that's okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That thing that cleaning and helping people, she brought it up in the session. That means something is churning inside her about the whole thing. She described the whole thing in a Rajasic mode, constantly smiling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Constantly smiling about it. And as soon as I… I asked the question thrice, first two times, she evaded the question.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That what will happen if you decide. And third time, when I pushed her to answer.
Dr. Karan Mittal: She went blank for a minute. And that is where your subcommode starts getting activated.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You start contemplating that, oh, I cannot see myself as different from a person who helps.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But I'm happy with that reality. Now, I would have pushed there. So that's how you work with changing the ghoulah. From a client who was fully Rajasik, describing, etc, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Switching it to self-contemplating.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Anandini Sundari DD: But I've not got this answered for me.
Anandini Sundari DD: I talked many times.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, you will get an answer. Maybe, maybe I'll send you a voice note, Mataji, to contemplate further on the answer. Yeah? This is how you…
Govinda Das ji: Yes, sorry, not what Karan said?
Govinda Das ji: You know, any action which involves helping others, is Rajobunam.
Govinda Das ji: Because there is an action.
Govinda Das ji: Right.
Govinda Das ji: And when people are doing something good, if you ask them to stop, they're blank.
Govinda Das ji: You know, sattvoguna is more of contemplation. There is a karuna. Karuna is sattvoguna, but action based on that karuna is Rajobuna.
Govinda Das ji: When Karuna has no action, then corona can lead to lamentation, that becomes Tamoga.
Govinda Das ji: Nope.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, when Karan asked this question at the last point.
Govinda Das ji: You are not able to… again, nobody can, not only… you are not able to conceive not doing that.
Govinda Das ji: So then that came the point of a reflection.
Govinda Das ji: So now, the deflection has not taken deeper aspect. When it goes deeper and deeper, you may find an answer based upon that reflection in context.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah.
Anandini Sundari DD: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that's what happens also, just giving a clinical thing. When you bring in something noble into the session, you know, some noble quality, like helping, philanthropy, all these things, we… there's a dead end. I cannot tell the person to stop helping people.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But what is Sato Mode? Knowing why you are doing what you are doing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If the person is not aware, why is he helping a person, despite the opposite person saying bad or doing bad to her? Then she's in auto mode. She's just helping people, but there are no answers to the question.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Sato mode is also doing things with awareness. It's… I cannot contradict the noble quality of helping people, because
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ethically, and there's… there's no human contradiction that can cancel that noble quality. That's how the world survives. But if that sattvic mode of not knowing, or not… she not knowing why she's doing this as a pattern or a loop, then she's not in the suffer mode of helping. She's in a Rajasic mode of helping, you know, auto-loop.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so… so, sorry, Madridji, I'll send you a voice note after the session to help you push this a bit further. Now we'll break out into rooms. Yeah, Ruthujaji? Yes. Well.
Rutuja Nayak: So,
Rutuja Nayak: See, even I have this, quality of, you know, wanting to help others in terms of fixing others. So, is it… is it always necessary that if a person who tends… who has this, intention of helping or fixing others needs to fix him herself or himself, is it always necessary, or it…
Rutuja Nayak: Depends.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Rabhuji, would you like to add some… add to this question?
Govinda Das ji: You know, nice question, it's a very important question. I have one very, very active counselor.
Govinda Das ji: Who has handled hundreds of cases.
Govinda Das ji: Right?
Govinda Das ji: And in one case, he was handling where he had spent 40 to 60…
Govinda Das ji: Hours dealing with one case, a conflict.
Govinda Das ji: And the father of the… one of the spouse.
Govinda Das ji: Became very angry and… very angry and upset with him.
Govinda Das ji: Even though you'd invested so much.
Govinda Das ji: Hi.
Govinda Das ji: And I was there. I was there when the father became angry with this one of my friends. When he came home.
Govinda Das ji: He told me a very interesting thing.
Govinda Das ji: He said, the need to help people is my gratification.
Govinda Das ji: I do not take it as a selfless service.
Govinda Das ji: If I take it to the selfless service, I feel why they're not reciprocating.
Govinda Das ji: He literally said Yamari Khuzhli, sorry to use this word, you know, he said that, you know, this is my itch.
Govinda Das ji: You know, I want to help people, whether they take it, don't take it, they take it. Otherwise, the impetus to help will not go away from me, because they mirror. And therefore, I don't see myself as a selfless server. I see my selfishness
Govinda Das ji: To help others.
Govinda Das ji: Imara Swarte, this is my selfishness.
Govinda Das ji: To help other. It makes me feel good. If I don't do that, I'll be disturbed, so therefore I won't.
Govinda Das ji: So therefore, yes, that was his upbringing, that was his disposition. Somebody else may do it as a responsibility.
Govinda Das ji: In the… in the… In the Bhakti literature, it is explained
Govinda Das ji: People serve God because of fear.
Govinda Das ji: People serve God because of hoping reward.
Govinda Das ji: People serve God because it is duty. People serve God because it is law.
Govinda Das ji: Either one of them. You know, they are fearful of ecostia.
Govinda Das ji: You know, so therefore, many times we do good things because we fear. We do good things because we feel rewarded.
Govinda Das ji: divide might come. They do good because we feel it is ambulatory mode, and sometimes we do good because they're not good.
Govinda Das ji: No, so therefore.
Govinda Das ji: So, when you, when you see these four things in three modes of material nature, three vonas, you know, as we do this exercise, you know, it will reflect, you know, why I do it.
Govinda Das ji: And that's sort of helping them to understand, why do I do this?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'll just add a bit, when you do it out of your inner vacuum of helping people, there's a tendency of us to overdo it.
Rutuja Nayak: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And that's what creates attachment to the results, you following up with the client, client not being interested. But where your inner core is satisfied, okay? Though you might still have some, like, monetary benefits, some happiness, some…
Dr. Karan Mittal: something that you get, but when majority of it is filled, then you won't overdo it. In fact, in Shastas also, it speaks, you don't advise unless you are classified.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But when you are into that Messiah-advised mode, Christ-saving mode, then you will overdo it.
Rutuja Nayak: Hmm.
Dr. Karan Mittal: many different, different ways. Falling up unnecessarily, giving too many advices, and then, you know, kind of being very clingy to the client. Many things come up, yeah?
Govinda Das ji: I've seen people, I've seen people who…
Govinda Das ji: When they do not do their spiritual practice.
Govinda Das ji: Others, those who don't do their spiritual practice, they become so concerned, or they are not doing their spiritual practice.
Govinda Das ji: So they become so disturbed, they actually disturb their own spiritual practices. You know? That also happens. So that is, like, concern at the cost of their own
Govinda Das ji: their own sadhana, which they have taken.
Govinda Das ji: As their own forms.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah.
Rutuja Nayak: Got it, thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so we'll do a 20 minutes breakout room.
Lavina Shewaramani: Awesome.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The observer's role, the third person's role.
Govinda Das ji: Listen, after the, after this session?
Lavina Shewaramani: Okay, okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, unless it is pertaining to the session.
Lavina Shewaramani: Yes. Yaya.
Dr. Karan Mittal: can do. Actually.
Lavina Shewaramani: Absolutely.
Lavina Shewaramani: Sorry. I'll ask later.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, yeah, that would be better tomorrow.
Govinda Das ji: Both. 11 years, yes.
Govinda Das ji: Both on the ground.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So the observer's role here, right, right now, one would be therapist, and observer's role is to keep the time to 7 minutes. 7 minutes you interrupt, 30 seconds the observer will share what worked, what didn't work, and then you switch. Keep, you know, don't…
Dr. Karan Mittal: become verbose, keep it to the point, so that the skill development happens. Sharing the whole thing, et cetera, can be done with a friend or a family member later, you know, learning the whole skillful. So, yeah, and we…
Govinda Das ji: What is the exercise? Clearly, what they need to do, and what.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So the demo I gave, that is the exercise that you will be doing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: 3 people, therapist, client, and observer.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Therapist will do the role what I did. Client will take up some superficial issue. One issue, don't, get into two, three issues. Just speak about one particular issue. Try to
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, client also facilitates it for the therapist, and then therapist asks the question to push the client into that self-reflective mode of, the guna, the sate guna, and the observer keeps the time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: observes what worked for the client and the therapist, what didn't work, and at the end, we'll comment in 30 seconds in pointers, okay?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so 7 to 8 minutes per book.
Renuka Bhuta: One, person who will be speaking, and so it will be 7 minutes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: One… there are 3 people, right? Everyone will take a turn to be each of their own, right? So, 7 minutes A and B, 7 minutes B and C, and 7 minutes A and C.
Renuka Bhuta: 21.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Therapist. 21 minutes, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I'm creating the groups.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You don't join, and I must sign, Veltice say, I think you have moderated.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oops.
Govinda Das ji: Fuck.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You can join any group rooms you want, yes.
Govinda Das ji: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Shubhamji, you might have to join. If you're not joining, then I'll give it to someone else.
Dr. Karan Mittal: A mute button.
DhyanShala: Yeah, I have clicked the joining link.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, fine.
DhyanShala: Please give it one smoke, if possible.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I… I'll put you in some other group tickets.
DhyanShala: Yeah, you're welcome.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Finally.
Dr. Karan Mittal: WG28 for 8… 37Y, I'll close it at 858.
Govinda Das ji: 30 minutes will go.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Teams.
Govinda Das ji: Mr. Coron?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Boji, they are returning back. Close the room, so it takes 60 seconds.
Govinda Das ji: This has to be done much more deeper.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Buji, maybe? Yeah.
Govinda Das ji: Is that one? No.
Govinda Das ji: The concept of Guna, we'll have to do more deeper.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Commissioner.
Govinda Das ji: Yep.
Govinda Das ji: Because we want to see how the shifting is happening.
Govinda Das ji: From Rajos to Tamar, Tamos to Raja, Rajos to Satwa.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, I think everyone's back.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, I think you can continue. I would just like to share one experience. So, if the… see, the client always knows more about his issue than you do.
Dr. Karan Mittal: There's no point… suppose a client is describing something, There's no point just…
Dr. Karan Mittal: asking more and more, more and more about that issue, per se. Now, if you see from an Indy perspective, if the client is talking about the chitta part, it's talking about memories and his vasnas and sanskaras and patterns. There's no point
Dr. Karan Mittal: In such a short session, asking more and more, more, and more details. The focus is to shift it to Buddhi, that Satric mode, or the contemplative mode, so that that vasna can be analyzed from the Buddhi's sattvic perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, in one of the sessions, for 7, 6-7 minutes, they were describing the whole thing, and just one question which kind of shifted the focus to Buddhi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: put the client into that contemplative mode of what could have changed, or how that pattern has affected you, or what if the pattern didn't exist, how would life be different? These things make you contemplate on the deeper
Dr. Karan Mittal: Effects, or effects of that particular
Dr. Karan Mittal: pattern, belief, Vasna on your life. And that's what the sagwic analysis from a Buddhist perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Who would you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so, yes. So, basically.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Western models, and again, this is what differs Indian models from the Western models. There are two major schools, which we have discussed in the first session. I'll just touch upon both the schools. One is what we saw, like John Locke.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Every person is like a blank slate. Tabula Rasa, he called it. So, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, whatever you want to condition the person, that is possible, as per that theory.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the second thing was seeing the client as a damaged default, in the sense that every person that comes to you is damaged because of some childhood reason. Freud called this because of the libido and the sexual urges in the childhood being misplaced, etc. So they saw that particular client as
Dr. Karan Mittal: the damaged one. And when you… what your conceptualization about the human being makes your therapy and diagnosis accordingly. So if you see a person as being damaged, you will, you know, kind of automatically
Dr. Karan Mittal: Act as that helper or the fixer in the client's life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you see that person as that blank slate, it will automatically try to impose more and more and more and more conditioning on that person's life. But the IKS sees, or the Indian Knowledge System sees a person very differently, which changes the perspective towards therapy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is… disturbing one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry, the slide got stuck.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Could you do… Yeah. Just move it for a minute, and then I'll just re-share this stuff.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Awesome. Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Rush.
Govinda Das ji: So therefore, as Karan was mentioning, the two theories, again in the Western world also, the free will.
Govinda Das ji: and destiny.
Govinda Das ji: There had some superimpose about free will.
Govinda Das ji: And it is not about religious people or…
Govinda Das ji: Non-religious people, even the scientific community has a conflict in regards to
Govinda Das ji: free will, or we are driven by neurological. You know, we have a pattern, and we simply respond to the pattern.
Govinda Das ji: like, I remember one, one, neurologist, and, he's, like, a scientist.
Govinda Das ji: and is an atheist in regards to Abrahamic religion. He asked this question, very important question.
Govinda Das ji: If I ask you now to remember a movie.
Govinda Das ji: Which movie will you remember? He asked that question.
Govinda Das ji: And then people talked about certain movies, whatever that scene.
Govinda Das ji: And he said, you can only remember those movies you have seen and you have heard about.
Govinda Das ji: You cannot remember about those movies if you have no background now, somewhere in India.
Govinda Das ji: He said, you cannot.
Govinda Das ji: So what does it show? It shows that you can only reflect, you can only contemplate based upon the impressions which are created in you. You do not have the freedom to think beyond your impressions.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, we do not have the free will.
Govinda Das ji: Very, very logical.
Govinda Das ji: Very reasonable. There is a lot of sense into that.
Govinda Das ji: But when you study the Bharatiya model, All impressions are circumstantial, situational.
Govinda Das ji: And therefore, This is very important to understand.
Govinda Das ji: In the Christian world, there is only two concepts, hell and heaven.
Govinda Das ji: Either you go to hell, or you go to heaven. There is no third concept existing.
Govinda Das ji: And what is hell? Hell is also eternal reality, eternally condemned.
Govinda Das ji: Or eternally rewarded.
Govinda Das ji: Either one of them.
Govinda Das ji: In the Bharati, which are a Ghara, health is not permanent.
Govinda Das ji: It is situational.
Govinda Das ji: It is circumstantial.
Govinda Das ji: And therefore, when Krishna says in the Gita, even if someone has done most abominable activity.
Govinda Das ji: If it takes shelter of these sachidan and the vigora, Alright? The Supreme Lord.
Govinda Das ji: Or the process of yoga, D…
Govinda Das ji: can be rectified, because we believe in
Govinda Das ji: The constitutional reality of full of knowledge, full of bliss, full of eternality. And therefore, even the most heinous crime
Govinda Das ji: Yes, legally history, which he or she should be punished, no doubt.
Govinda Das ji: But philosophically and psychologically, even they can be rectified. If not today, In some point of time.
Govinda Das ji: And that is the base of the Jiva, and therefore, Bharti, which are the Indian Knowledge System, what does it do? It integrates between the crime and the disease.
Govinda Das ji: Disease is curable, Crime has to be punished.
Govinda Das ji: Please understand. The crime has to be punished.
Govinda Das ji: So what are we doing? We are not punishing the person, we are punishing the crime committed by the person.
Govinda Das ji: hoping that, and therefore that capital punishment in the Hindu scripture
Govinda Das ji: One reason is, okay, punish them, capitally give them death penalty, so that they will not perform crime once again.
Govinda Das ji: That is a pure logic of crime and punishment.
Govinda Das ji: The second logic Srila Prabhupam again explains
Govinda Das ji: Is that if you punish them now.
Govinda Das ji: Rather than suffering so much more.
Govinda Das ji: Next life, they'll get an opportunity to come back and rectify their mistake. This is very important. Therefore, Sachita Ananda, it is not simply a philosophy. It has a practical application in regards to dealing with our clients.
Govinda Das ji: It gives the rise to hope.
Govinda Das ji: It gives rise to a process to be given to them.
Govinda Das ji: You know, therefore you'll read in the scripture.
Govinda Das ji: You know, even somebody has done the most abominable activity of breaking the deities, Alright?
Govinda Das ji: Or somebody has done the activity of killing the cow, according to Hindu literature, or Dharmic literature.
Govinda Das ji: Right? It's a heinous crime, but still there is a process of rectification. It is not eternally condemned.
Govinda Das ji: You know, they show the extreme. Extreme reactive behavior at the same time there is a solution, and where does it emanate from? It emanates from the position of full of knowledge, full of bliss, full of eternality. This is not only a religious assertation.
Govinda Das ji: It is deeply rooted in human psychology.
Govinda Das ji: And it helps the therapist to deal with their clients properly.
Govinda Das ji: No.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I think that's what… I think… I think Prabhuji has explained it very nicely, that if you believe that the core is damaged, then you are the Messiah, you are the Helper, you are the one who's going to
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, liberate the client, or you are going to try to, probably bring him out of that whole, whole thing. So, your perspective or your disposition to the whole thing changes, and when you are getting that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Satisfaction, or that… that kick of helping the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: or kind of liberating the client, then automatically you try to engage or indulge more into his things that are not required, things you go… you kind of overindulge yourself. But if you are here just as a container, you know that the client is
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sached Ananda is resolved, only there are coverings that are probably, you know, affecting him right now, then you automatically take two steps back, and then you are able to view the situation also like a third person, not engaging into that entanglement or
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or that attachment to the client. And when you are watching it as a third person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: with this belief, the solutions that you suggest are more effective, and that you'll be able to observe and experience only with practice. The more you see the situation with a different perspective, a third-person perspective and a distant perspective, the better you are able to help the kind. But more entangled you are.
Dr. Karan Mittal: with your own inner vacuums, and in your own inner needs to liberate the client and help the client, the more and more
Dr. Karan Mittal: difficult the therapy becomes, the more problematic it also becomes to you. Then you bring these clients back at your home.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, trying to solve the problem in your head also, every now and then, 24 by 7, you are engaged in two actions. So as a therapist, having that distinct view is important, and that comes from the perspective at which you conceptualize a client or a case.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Georgia.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, and therefore, again, this is another very profound concept.
Govinda Das ji: that… Karma, the set of gods.
Govinda Das ji: You know, there is karma. Now, karma itself has two meaning, okay?
Govinda Das ji: One of the tragedy of… People who teach karma, and those who understand karma.
Govinda Das ji: You know, what is it karma means?
Govinda Das ji: Karma means basically, oh, I need to simply accept the reality of my life, however it comes.
Govinda Das ji: For example, there is a big difference.
Govinda Das ji: Like, someone you see Being slapped repeatedly again and again.
Govinda Das ji: And what happens?
Govinda Das ji: You do not have the power to stop the person from slapping.
Govinda Das ji: So what do you do, in your mind.
Govinda Das ji: To avoid your own limitation of stopping.
Govinda Das ji: You may say, oh, she or he's suffering her karma.
Govinda Das ji: Again, we can extend this example.
Govinda Das ji: Then, back… In the days, now also it happens, when a girl goes to her husband's place.
Govinda Das ji: And she's abused.
Govinda Das ji: What does she does? She does talk to her parents.
Govinda Das ji: But sometimes, the parents, without getting into the details.
Govinda Das ji: They may only say, Betty, what can be done? This is part of your karma.
Govinda Das ji: You know, accept this as your reality, move on.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, nowadays, people are…
Govinda Das ji: so reactive, they don't even talk about karma, they suddenly try to break, they go for radical justice.
Govinda Das ji: So here, it is not karma, it is Anyaya, it is injustice.
Govinda Das ji: Alright, so we have to separate karma and industries.
Govinda Das ji: Please understand, seeing injustice as their karma itself is a bad karma we are accumulating.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, what is karma? Karma is past, and karma also means action.
Govinda Das ji: The philosophy of karma, when we say, oh, this is what is the reality, you can only say that if you do not have access to the reason why someone is suffering, you have the access to that.
Govinda Das ji: Another pessimistic question people ask, if somebody's going through disease.
Govinda Das ji: And if the doctor is intervening into that, is it not that we're interfering into their karma? This is the worst way to understand karma.
Govinda Das ji: Such questions should not even arise.
Govinda Das ji: Because very definition of karma is, if I'm going through some disease.
Govinda Das ji: The principle of karma says, yes, you're going through certain disease because whatever reason passed, but now it's your karma means action to deal with it properly.
Govinda Das ji: So, please understand, karma is a reflection of the past.
Govinda Das ji: And karma as done action for the present and the future. That is the definition of karma. And a Purushartha.
Govinda Das ji: Now, this word, Purush Shorta, means Putting in effort, endeavor.
Govinda Das ji: Purusha means here, human being.
Govinda Das ji: Alright, Purusha denotes to man and woman both, where there is an action. In the Bhagavad Gita. Beautiful! Very interesting. Sri Krishna explains to Arjuna.
Govinda Das ji: I am the ability in human being.
Govinda Das ji: When you turn around, when you're able to turn around, I was,
Govinda Das ji: talking to one young man, I know him since he was in his childhood.
Govinda Das ji: And he has told me, you can share this story too with people, and therefore I'm sharing, because it was very private.
Govinda Das ji: He went through very painful childhood.
Govinda Das ji: Extremely painful childhood.
Govinda Das ji: Because of incompatible parents.
Govinda Das ji: Mother went through some health situation.
Govinda Das ji: And because of that, a young boy had to experience misunderstanding from the mother to the extent where she was used by some people to file a case against her own son. Yeah.
Govinda Das ji: Hello?
Govinda Das ji: Able to hear?
Vikram Chakilam: Now it's okay, approachable, but 10 seconds ago, you were breaking up.
Govinda Das ji: Okay, sorry. Are you able to hear now?
Vikram Chakilam: Yes, Pravit. You were saying about the mother.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah. So… She passed away recently.
Govinda Das ji: And 3 months before passing away.
Govinda Das ji: You know, she experienced amazing transformation.
Govinda Das ji: The boy who had gone through a lot of painful reality.
Govinda Das ji: You know, it changed the entire mindset of his.
Govinda Das ji: just before she passed away, and he was not responsible for Iventure.
Govinda Das ji: He fought against his odd karma.
Govinda Das ji: You know, he rectified his own physical limitation, never changed his mind of supporting his mother.
Govinda Das ji: And he always remembered this loka, I would teach him this loka.
Govinda Das ji: I am the ability in human being.
Govinda Das ji: This is one of the most profound shlocas in the Bhagavad Gita.
Govinda Das ji: Your ability is synonymous to God itself.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, the Bharatiya model is the model of rectification, reformation, and evolution.
Govinda Das ji: And therefore, karma and Purshartha, they're interconnected in regards to what they mean.
Govinda Das ji: And then Punar Jammu.
Govinda Das ji: What is Pularjanma? Getting an… another opportunity.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, some people take it for granted.
Govinda Das ji: But mostly, if this opportunity is not there.
Govinda Das ji: Imagine only one chance, and you're doomed.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, karma, Purushartha, and Punarjanma has to be, again, visualized not purely as, oh, it's a Hindu belief, or the belief of the Sanat and Dharma, but this is how Prakriti operates.
Govinda Das ji: She gives an opportunity.
Govinda Das ji: She… Use the persist2 function.
Govinda Das ji: And when you fail to process the function, she gives another opportunity
Govinda Das ji: To… to come back and begin from very often.
Govinda Das ji: Nope.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, that is the… this three principle, huh?
Govinda Das ji: resolution.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You can take questions from me.
Govinda Das ji: Yup.
Govinda Das ji: Any questions or comments?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Suraj Racha: Thank you.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah.
Suraj Racha: Rudy, I have a question. So actually.
Suraj Racha: I may sound a little more trivial here, but initially, we were… initially, like, we were having some kind of
Suraj Racha: understanding that, okay, Hattva Gunna is better, then followed by Raja, followed by Tamil, and that conception was maintained for, for some time. But now, when we were discuss,
Suraj Racha: discussing that all of them do have their own advantages, and they have their places. Now, honestly, I got even more confused, as in, if a client is there, then what exactly should we be suggesting them?
Suraj Racha: Like, should we suggest them to slowly push to the platform of sattva, or should we also acknowledge the Rajas and Tamas and try to stabilize them?
Govinda Das ji: That's what Karan, you want to address, because he focused on that. You are not supposed to, you know, push them to come to Sattva, you have to observe
Govinda Das ji: How they're operating.
Govinda Das ji: You know, and what is their position? Like, the first, when we… when he did that demo exercise with Mataji, Anand, Sundari Mataji, you know, all her happiness, why she likes to do, what she likes to do, when he pushed her by asking questions, what he did.
Govinda Das ji: You know, she was explaining her experience of Rajo Guna.
Govinda Das ji: By pushing her, he made her reflect.
Govinda Das ji: Because it was only 5-6 minutes, if it pushed further, more, and more, showed…
Govinda Das ji: facilitated herself, through the support of Karan.
Govinda Das ji: You know, to become more reflected.
Govinda Das ji: Right, so your responsibility is to bring the concept of reflection, and reflection happens through Satvaguna.
Govinda Das ji: You are not making them give up Rajo Guna and only focus on Satwoman.
Govinda Das ji: Because if you're an 18-year-old, 26-year-old, 30-year-old man or a woman.
Govinda Das ji: That is the time you are expanding, whether it is your business, your family, your entrepreneurship, Alright?
Govinda Das ji: So if you make them stop and focus only in Satvaguna.
Govinda Das ji: So what does it do? And if they are not naturally interested in mukti, that becomes counterproductive.
Govinda Das ji: Like, Arjuna wanted to live by begging.
Govinda Das ji: Was it possible for Arjuna to live by begging? It is not possible.
Govinda Das ji: If a businessman is there, suddenly gives up the business, and you make him join some ashram.
Govinda Das ji: There, also, he'll find many opportunities, or at least his mind will be having a disposition of making business and money.
Govinda Das ji: Right? I'm sitting in some tirtha, holy place, We had some work here.
Govinda Das ji: And you can see, like, one person was telling me, that this place, people in cities do ethical business.
Govinda Das ji: But when it is a religious place.
Govinda Das ji: You know, forget about ethical business. It is brutal, simply, money-making at the cost of the pilgrims.
Govinda Das ji: I'm not saying everybody, but many people do like that.
Govinda Das ji: So, even though being in the spiritual place, Their Rajobun is so toxic.
Govinda Das ji: Right. So, very important for us to understand, we as the therapist, we are not pushing them to become artificially in Sakhavana.
Govinda Das ji: We are simply helping them to observe.
Govinda Das ji: You want them to observe. Observation comes from Satvaguna. Based on that observation, you'll help them to see how much Rajo Ghuna they need, how much thermoguna they need, and accordingly, you facilitate.
Govinda Das ji: Does that make sense?
Suraj Racha: Yes, yes.
Suraj Racha: Thank you.
Govinda Das ji: Sure.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I'll just add a bit, Roji, I think,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, this hierarchy of gunas comes from a very spiritual angle, but if you see the sankhya yoga, all the three gunas are considered equal, actually.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And without Rajas Goda, Satvaya and Thomas don't function.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, all the gunas, it's called as Sri Guna Meka Prakriti. So, all the three gunas are equally important as per Sankhya Darshan, not Sankhy Yoga.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's… it's like what you need at particular time is very important. On a therapist's chair, in a therapist's room, you need that satra lens to the situation for the client to go self-contemplate it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if I was a sports trainer, training a person for marathon, I will not push the client for Satrapuna. Then I need the Rajabot.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, there is no hierarchy, it's what you need at that particular point of time. And suppose a client comes to me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: with Tamogana domination, probably I might not even try to push him at Sakuraguna in the first session itself. Maybe I'll bring him to Rajuana first, trying to make him a bit more active, etc, and then bring him to Sakwa. So there's no hierarchy. The sakva gives us lens to go deeper.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, come up with solutions to the problem.
Dr. Karan Mittal: there's no… this… like, there's no hierarchy that firsts are resistant, come unknown, nothing of that sort. That's what I said in the beginning. These are… these are not moral biases, these are not moral combatments that this client is bad, this is good, this is this. This is just what you need in that therapist to add reputability.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Jenu G, I guess.
jithendra myla: So, Pravi, about karmic, karma subject.
jithendra myla: where…
jithendra myla: A lot of times, I get puzzled by looking at, you know, in the news we see in Africa, where kids have to suffer, extreme poverty, and then…
jithendra myla: They don't even have basic humanities, like drinking water or proper shelter.
jithendra myla: I'm… What karma did in their previous life to take,
jithendra myla: to suffer like this, like, sometimes I feel like there is…
jithendra myla: What's the point of going to hell if you can't suffer the hellish life in planet Earth only?
jithendra myla: So, that… Karma part of that, puzzles me sometimes.
Govinda Das ji: Again, I'll answer, and then Karan Ancel can add.
Govinda Das ji: So, when you study carefully material nature, material nature.
Govinda Das ji: If you go to any part of the world.
Govinda Das ji: According to where people have gone, there is food, there is water, there is air.
Govinda Das ji: Whether you go to Africa, whether you go to South America, whether you go to, you know, even the most… the remotest part of India.
Govinda Das ji: Where there is lack of resources, but still there are resources.
Govinda Das ji: As long as human beings don't interfere.
Govinda Das ji: People live according to their upbringing, their situation, their surroundings.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, when you see from a purely sattubona perspective.
Govinda Das ji: You can create gradations. Oh, there is Tamogonam much here, or there is Satogona here.
Govinda Das ji: That is Rajobunahi.
Govinda Das ji: Right.
Govinda Das ji: But this suffering, generally, It is caused because of exploitation of the few elite.
Govinda Das ji: you know, the… the… again, Srila Faupad also explains
Govinda Das ji: But most people are weak and sinful because of their activities.
Govinda Das ji: But there are few who are having a rakshasi consciousness, rakshasi Guru.
Govinda Das ji: Where they store all the resources at one place, exploit others.
Govinda Das ji: So that is injustice. If you carefully observe.
Govinda Das ji: There is more injustice caused by the human being.
Govinda Das ji: Rather than Prakriti, because Prakriti is extremely resourceful in providing
Govinda Das ji: Okay, yes, their food habits may not be correct.
Govinda Das ji: from the perspective of Satoguna.
Govinda Das ji: But they have the food.
Govinda Das ji: Slowly, slowly, they might evolve. Therefore, human beings are 8. There are 400,000 varieties of human beings.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Like, take, for example, Africa.
Govinda Das ji: It's a land of prosperity not properly utilized.
Govinda Das ji: you know, today we were studying something on, if you study Europe, 15th century Europe.
Govinda Das ji: before Enlightenment, before the Protestant movement.
Govinda Das ji: Prosperity was seen as a sin.
Govinda Das ji: Prosperity and economical development was seen from the moral perspective.
Govinda Das ji: To the extent where people took so seriously, that… the… the rich…
Govinda Das ji: will not enter into the kingdom of God.
Govinda Das ji: In fact, some historians have written Jesus Christ was the original socialist.
Govinda Das ji: Nope.
Govinda Das ji: After the… after the Enlightenment period, people like Adam Smith.
Govinda Das ji: They said… they said, separate prosperity development from piety.
Govinda Das ji: You know, let us separate them. And that is already existing in Bharata, Dharma, Artha, karma.
Govinda Das ji: You know, earning wealth.
Govinda Das ji: Dharmikali is not a Papa, it was never a papa, therefore we always have Lakshmi and Lara in together.
Govinda Das ji: You know? So, therefore.
Govinda Das ji: If you study carefully, let us not see from, oh, they must have done bad karma.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, you can see from, again, Buddhas. You have certain habits, they have different habits.
Govinda Das ji: We can see that GONA perspective.
Govinda Das ji: But from the karma perspective, it is more injustice.
Govinda Das ji: I was talking to a very, very well-placed Air Force officer. He just retired as the Vice Air Marshal of India, Vice Air Chief Marshal.
Govinda Das ji: He said 10 countries' budget. For one year, they do not spend on the defense budget for 1 year.
Govinda Das ji: We're not saying every year. He said, 10 countries, if they do not spend their budget for one year. He said, every country will have a drinking water.
Govinda Das ji: Every country will have a good health system.
Govinda Das ji: Every country will have a good educational system.
Govinda Das ji: Every country will have a good connecting system. He said, I'm not speaking emotionally. He said, I'm speaking statistically. He said, but we don't need it.
Govinda Das ji: No, yes, there is more injustice
Govinda Das ji: and less discussion of karma. We should discuss more about injustice rather than discussing of karma, because karma is very, very judgmental sometimes.
Govinda Das ji: Okay. Yep.
Govinda Das ji: Sorry for the long answer.
Govinda Das ji: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any other question?
Lavina Shewaramani: May I ask?
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, you had a…
Lavina Shewaramani: Yeah, like, supposing we were talking about being a philanthropist and helping. That is sattva Gun. But the intention behind that sometimes comes out to be a Rajas Gun.
Lavina Shewaramani: So, there's a difference of guna. So, which is more dominating? Is it the action or the intention? Like, how would we know which is more strong?
Govinda Das ji: Action without… action without intention becomes the mode eventually.
Govinda Das ji: You know, if you do not have the resources to help.
Govinda Das ji: You want to help, and you don't have the resources to help, then you'll start lamenting.
Govinda Das ji: And lamentation is come over now.
Govinda Das ji: You can't just feel for people, you need to do something good for people.
Govinda Das ji: We are only feeling we are not able to good, that gives rise to pain also.
Lavina Shewaramani: Like you said, intention is gratification. Somebody, you gave example. So, maybe a philanthropist is helping, a person is helping, is a sattva girl, but his intention behind that is, like, you know, to, because of his ego, or maybe he wants sense gratification, too. That is a Rajas guru.
Lavina Shewaramani: So what is more dominating as a personality? Like, is it… is it the action or the intention being in, like, you know.
Lavina Shewaramani: Or gratification, since breath.
Govinda Das ji: And it depends person to person. You know, even though somebody's… even though someone may do the action, you know, 40% action, 70%, 60% is stronger intention.
Govinda Das ji: Then you know that intention is dominating, but action is also involved.
Govinda Das ji: And somebody may not think about the intention, just do that.
Govinda Das ji: You don't need to do it, you know, just like a… just like an… And an administrative officer.
Govinda Das ji: IS officer, he's providing resources to the state or the city, duty-bound. He's not thinking so much about compassion, he's thinking about process.
Govinda Das ji: I need to provide water to so many people. I need to provide electricity to so many people.
Govinda Das ji: He's not saying from the Daiya perspective, he's saying from the getting things done perspective.
Govinda Das ji: You know, so, one is… one is judging your own self.
Govinda Das ji: And second, judging based upon how does it contribute?
Govinda Das ji: This one's empty.
Govinda Das ji: If it is contributing to society favorably.
Govinda Das ji: It doesn't matter what is the intention, he has to deal with his own intention.
Govinda Das ji: We'll take it. Some people are…
Govinda Das ji: Very boastful, they want to do charity, but they want to show everywhere.
Govinda Das ji: You know, all newspaper, all television, everywhere, right? It doesn't matter, that's his problem.
Govinda Das ji: He or she has to deal with it. But the society is benefited by those resources.
Govinda Das ji: One may say, but there is a contamination of their godas, it doesn't matter.
Govinda Das ji: At least it is benefiting. I want to give 50,000 cycles.
Govinda Das ji: But I'm a big mafia.
Govinda Das ji: Alright? My money has come from all badmins.
Govinda Das ji: So I want to purify myself by giving some charity.
Govinda Das ji: So, that is my problem to deal with it, but that 50,000 bicycles will help so many people.
Govinda Das ji: Even the intention is wrong, But the consequences of the charity will benefit to the people.
Govinda Das ji: So this is a very complex…
Govinda Das ji: but understandable situation. It takes what they reflect
Govinda Das ji: You know, again, shattoo Gun mein attagi, you'll get to know, okay, what is intention, what is action, what are the consequences, how it is beneficial.
Govinda Das ji: All that one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just add, from a psychological perspective, so, if we go from a Mimansa, Memansa is, like, we have Sankhya, we have Nyaya, we have Mimansa, the shin.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The terminology karum is for the intention, and the actual action that you do in the world is kriya.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so whenever you have that intention, that is karma, and the physical action becomes clear. Now, you said
Dr. Karan Mittal: If I'm doing it for sense gratification, then my karma is sense gratification, and the kriya is doing that punya, or that philanthropy, etc. So now my question is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Will that Kriya give me Pune or no? Yes, it will give me punya.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But because my karma is more Rajasik, and if not sattvik, then that kriya will fail to keep on satisfying me in a long term. In the sense, I might keep on doing that Kriya, kriya, Kriya, kriya, but internally, I will still feel that vacuum.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes, the Rajasikh will be dominant, and that is leading to something good for the society. Punya will get generated, but will it transform something within? Long-term, the answer is no. Short-term gratification? Yes. But long-term, either the person goes in an expanding loop of doing more, more, more, more, more.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or that vacuum still stays. So unless that sarthwik karma creates a sarvik area outside, that loop
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of internal satisfaction doesn't come I think, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What makes that service?
DhyanShala: Oh, yeah.
DhyanShala: Yeah. Yeah, I have one.
Govinda Das ji: Correct.
DhyanShala: Yeah, Travuji, I have one question for you. During the explanation, you've told about capital punishment.
DhyanShala: And you… You described it as…
DhyanShala: If you've punish them now, then there is a chance that in their next birth, Unarjan, they'll have less suffering.
DhyanShala: So, but there is also one concept of,
DhyanShala: The kerm that you have performed, the full will definitely merge.
DhyanShala: And until and unless you have not completed its consumption of that bulk, You have to take rebirth.
Govinda Das ji: Hmm.
DhyanShala: So, if that person to whom we are allotting capital punishment, if he has not completed his…
DhyanShala: Then, definitely, suffering will be continued in next birth also.
Govinda Das ji: So, again, it can be seen from different, different perspectives. One perspective which is seen is that when I said… like, I give you this example. I remember, you know, someone who has done the act of abusing a person, woman.
Govinda Das ji: You know, so… And then he repents.
Govinda Das ji: Genuinely repents.
Govinda Das ji: Fair enough.
DhyanShala: Let's shut down.
Govinda Das ji: Pashtraka, genuinely repents, then the question is read.
Govinda Das ji: The question is raised, should he be forgiven?
Govinda Das ji: Okay, all… there are so many people here, all the ladies are there, what do you think, ladies? What should be done with it?
Lavina Shewaramani: I guess half karma is forgiven, half he has to suffer, that's what I have.
Govinda Das ji: What do you want to do? What do you want? You are a judge, what will you do? If you see that he's, you know, repenting seriously, then what will you do? Will you give him a death penalty, or will you say, okay, Jane, I'll give 14 years in prison? What will you do?
Lavina Shewaramani: done this.
Govinda Das ji: What's happening here? What will you do?
Lavina Shewaramani: Janeto Prabhuji.
Govinda Das ji: Jane, gotcha. What you'll say, Jane, though, you'll forgive him?
Lavina Shewaramani: Yeah, subject bunaman.
Govinda Das ji: Love shot.
Govinda Das ji: Others? Anybody else?
jithendra myla: 14-year imprisonment.
Govinda Das ji: pertini and…
jithendra myla: You said 14-year imprisonment, or the death sentence, like, 14 years…
Govinda Das ji: I just knew that.
jithendra myla: there is some, punishment should be there.
Govinda Das ji: So, so therefore what the justice says… Even? Anybody else?
DhyanShala: Yeah, I would like to add that, if punishment… if Prayashtit is very genuine, then it is very close to punishment itself.
Govinda Das ji: crashed as genuine.
Govinda Das ji: But still, because the act of abusing a person
Govinda Das ji: And if he's forgiven, it sets a wrong thread amongst others to feel that I can't try once.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, even if the Puraprayashtit is very genuine, it is good for his mental karma, but the punishment has to be given death penalty so that others
Govinda Das ji: do not take, you know, advantage, okay? The punishment has to be.
Govinda Das ji: And secondly, the Prashtit is there.
Govinda Das ji: Right? That benefits his karma, and death penalty also benefits him
Govinda Das ji: Because when his life is abruptly ended.
Govinda Das ji: For the crime he or she did.
Govinda Das ji: So, next life, yes, it is not that they're completely overcome, because punishment does not…
Govinda Das ji: Help you progress. Yoga helps you to progress.
Govinda Das ji: There was only danda, yoga na yoga, so there is less consequences unless one performs active yoga, jhyana yoga, Ashtang yoga, bhakti yoga, karma yoga.
Govinda Das ji: One cannot overcome the consequences of karma. It is simply.
DhyanShala: It totally depends upon his own poor Sharth.
Govinda Das ji: Yes! That is the only thing. Others cannot punish and free us and forgive us and free us. It is the personal responsibility of the Jeep.
Govinda Das ji: So next week, what we will do, because we have few more things to do, if you can join with us at 7 o'clock.
Govinda Das ji: You know, if it is not a problem, then we take a longer session. Today, we had to
Govinda Das ji: Cut short few slides, and then Punchakosha Adharit concept we will teach for our kids.
Govinda Das ji: So then we can join at 7 o'clock. Next, we will also send
Govinda Das ji: A reminder. Thank you for your kind action. Attention will stop here.
Govinda Das ji: Topping.
Renuka Bhuta: Thank you, Perfectly.
jithendra myla: Beautiful.
Lavina Shewaramani: Thank you.